<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<MSS id="1ABABFA20Zz06-asx30Zz06-11E20Zz06-90F80Zz06-C8549DFF4B22156pol7890Zz06">
<TIMESTAMP>2015-10-22 10:55:42</TIMESTAMP><STATE code='AR'>Arkansas</STATE><TITLE>Curriculum Framework</TITLE><SOURCE>http://www.arkansased.gov/divisions/learning-services/curriculum-and-instruction/curriculum-framework-documents/english-language-arts</SOURCE><SUBJECT code="LANG" seq="10">English Language Arts</SUBJECT><YEAR>2015</YEAR>
<STANDARD id="B458F7F2-D959-11E2-9C66-33FC9CFF4B22"><GRADE lo="K" hi="12" seq="350" code="K12">College- and Career-Readiness Anchor Standards Enhanced to 12</GRADE>
<TOPIC id="FC2B3CE0-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="QS 007" label="Strand" seq="1" level="1" placeholder="N" linkable="N">Reading UPDATED 1.0<TOPIC id="FC3F8786-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC2B3CE0-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" seq="2" level="2" placeholder="N" linkable="N">Key Ideas and Details UPDATED 1.0<TOPIC id="FCECE50C-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC3F8786-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="QS 007" raw_state_num="1" label="Anchor Standard" seq="3" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Read closely to determine what the text says explicitly and to make logical inferences from it; cite specific textual evidence when writing or speaking to support conclusions drawn from the text UPDATED 1.2.<TOPIC id="FCECE50C1-D90C1-11E21-8CB51-43E6D51F4EFCX1" parent_id="FCECE50C-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="QS 007" raw_state_num="1" label="Anchor Standard" seq="3" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Key Ideas and Details UPDATED 1.3.<TOPIC id="FCECE50C12-D90C12-11E212-8CB512-43E6D51F4EFCX12" parent_id="FCECE50C1-D90C1-11E21-8CB51-43E6D51F4EFCX1" state_num="QS 007" raw_state_num="1" label="Anchor Standard" seq="3" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Key Ideas and Details UPDATED 1.4.<TOPIC id="FCECE50C123-D90C123-11E2123-8CB5123-43E6D51F4EFCX123" parent_id="FCECE50C12-D90C12-11E212-8CB512-43E6D51F4EFCX12" state_num="QS 007" raw_state_num="1" label="Anchor Standard" seq="3" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Key Ideas and Details UPDATED 1.5.<TOPIC id="FCECE50C123-D90C123-11E2123-8CB5123-43E6D51F4EFCX123" parent_id="FCECE50C12-D90C12-11E212-8CB512-43E6D51F4EFCX12" state_num="QS 007" raw_state_num="1" label="Anchor Standard" seq="3" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Key Ideas and Details UPDATED 1.6.
</TOPIC>
</TOPIC>
</TOPIC>
</TOPIC>
</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FCF2E9CA-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC3F8786-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="R.2" raw_state_num="2" label="Anchor Standard" seq="4" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Determine central ideas or themes of a text and analyze their development; summarize the key supporting details and ideas.</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FCF92632-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC3F8786-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="R.3" raw_state_num="3" label="Anchor Standard" seq="5" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Analyze how and why individuals, events, and ideas develop and interact over the course of a text.</TOPIC>
</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FC4582C6-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC2B3CE0-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" seq="6" level="2" placeholder="N" linkable="N">Craft and Structure<TOPIC id="FD01D20A-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC4582C6-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="R.4" raw_state_num="4" label="Anchor Standard" seq="7" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Interpret words and phrases as they are used in a text, including determining technical, connotative, and figurative meanings, and analyze how specific word choices shape meaning or tone.</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FD18D14E-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC4582C6-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="R.5" raw_state_num="5" label="Anchor Standard" seq="8" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Analyze the structure of texts, including how specific sentences, paragraphs, and larger portions of the text (e.g., a section, chapter, scene, or stanza) relate to each other and the whole.</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FD21305A-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC4582C6-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="R.6" raw_state_num="6" label="Anchor Standard" seq="9" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Assess how point of view or purpose shapes the content and style of a text.</TOPIC>
</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FC593D84-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC2B3CE0-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" seq="10" level="2" placeholder="N" linkable="N">Integration of Knowledge and Ideas<TOPIC id="FD2866E0-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC593D84-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="R.7" raw_state_num="7" label="Anchor Standard" seq="11" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Integrate and evaluate content presented in diverse media and formats, including visually and quantitatively, as well as in words.<EXTENDEDTOPIC>Please see &#8220;Research to Build and Present Knowledge&#8221; in Writing and &#8220;Comprehension and Collaboration&#8221; in Speaking and Listening for additional standards relevant to gathering, assessing, and applying information from print and digital sources.</EXTENDEDTOPIC></TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FD2D4746-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC593D84-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="R.8" raw_state_num="8" label="Anchor Standard" seq="12" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Delineate and evaluate the argument and specific claims in a text, including the validity of the reasoning as well as the relevance and sufficiency of the evidence.</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FD327680-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC593D84-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="R.9" raw_state_num="9" label="Anchor Standard" seq="13" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Analyze how two or more texts address similar themes or topics in order to build knowledge or to compare the approaches the authors take.</TOPIC>
</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FC5F2D16-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC2B3CE0-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" seq="14" level="2" placeholder="N" linkable="N">Range of Reading and Level of Text Complexity<TOPIC id="FD381D42-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC5F2D16-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="R.10" raw_state_num="10" label="Anchor Standard" seq="15" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Read and comprehend complex literary and informational texts independently and proficiently.</TOPIC>
</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FC64706E-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC2B3CE0-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="Note" raw_state_num="Note" seq="16" level="2" placeholder="N" linkable="N">Note on range and content of student reading<TOPIC id="FD3F53AA-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC64706E-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="Note" raw_state_num="Note" seq="17" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">K-5 To build a foundation for college and career readiness, students must read widely and deeply from among a broad range of high-quality, increasingly challenging literary and informational texts. Through extensive reading of stories, dramas, poems, and myths from diverse cultures and different time periods, students gain literary and cultural knowledge as well as familiarity with various text structures and elements. By reading texts in history/social studies, science, and other disciplines, students build a foundation of knowledge in these fields that will also give them the background to be better readers in all content areas. Students can only gain this foundation when the curriculum is intentionally and coherently structured to develop rich content knowledge within and across grades. Students also acquire the habits of reading independently and closely, which are essential to their future success.</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FD44ABD4-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC64706E-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="Note" raw_state_num="Note" seq="18" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">6-12 To become college and career ready, students must grapple with works of exceptional craft and thought whose range extends across genres, cultures, and centuries. Such works offer profound insights into the human condition and serve as models for students&#8217; own thinking and writing. Along with high-quality contemporary works, these texts should be chosen from among seminal U.S. documents, the classics of American literature, and the timeless dramas of Shakespeare. Through wide and deep reading of literature and literary nonfiction of steadily increasing sophistication, students gain a reservoir of literary and cultural knowledge, references, and images; the ability to evaluate intricate arguments; and the capacity to surmount the challenges posed by complex texts.</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FD598C20-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC64706E-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="Note" raw_state_num="Note" seq="19" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">6-12.WHST Reading is critical to building knowledge in history/social studies as well as in science and technical subjects. College and career ready reading in these fields requires an appreciation of the norms and conventions of each discipline, such as the kinds of evidence used in history and science; an understanding of domain-specific words and phrases; an attention to precise details; and the capacity to evaluate intricate arguments, synthesize complex information, and follow detailed descriptions of events and concepts. In history/social studies, for example, students need to be able to analyze, evaluate, and differentiate primary and secondary sources. When reading scientific and technical texts, students need to be able to gain knowledge from challenging texts that often make extensive use of elaborate diagrams and data to convey information and illustrate concepts. Students must be able to read complex informational texts in these fields with independence and confidence because the vast majority of reading in college and workforce training programs will be sophisticated nonfiction. It is important to note that these Reading standards are meant to complement the specific content demands of the disciplines, not replace them.</TOPIC>
</TOPIC>
</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FC30E83E-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="W" label="Strand" seq="20" level="1" placeholder="N" linkable="N">Writing<TOPIC id="FC6D6A20-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC30E83E-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" seq="21" level="2" placeholder="N" linkable="N">Text Types and Purposes<EXTENDEDTOPIC>These broad types of writing include many subgenres.</EXTENDEDTOPIC><TOPIC id="FD5F1230-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC6D6A20-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="W.1" raw_state_num="1" label="Anchor Standard" seq="22" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Write arguments to support claims in an analysis of substantive topics or texts, using valid reasoning and relevant and sufficient evidence.</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FD64C00E-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC6D6A20-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="W.2" raw_state_num="2" label="Anchor Standard" seq="23" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Write informative/explanatory texts to examine and convey complex ideas and information clearly and accurately through the effective selection, organization, and analysis of content.</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FD7FD088-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC6D6A20-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="W.3" raw_state_num="3" label="Anchor Standard" seq="24" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Write narratives to develop real or imagined experiences or events using effective technique, well-chosen details, and well-structured event sequences.</TOPIC>
</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FC75EEFC-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC30E83E-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" seq="25" level="2" placeholder="N" linkable="N">Production and Distribution of Writing<TOPIC id="FD85559E-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC75EEFC-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="W.4" raw_state_num="4" label="Anchor Standard" seq="26" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Produce clear and coherent writing in which the development, organization, and style are appropriate to task, purpose, and audience.</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FD99CD80-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC75EEFC-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="W.5" raw_state_num="5" label="Anchor Standard" seq="27" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Develop and strengthen writing as needed by planning, revising, editing, rewriting, or trying a new approach.</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FDA4E01C-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC75EEFC-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="W.6" raw_state_num="6" label="Anchor Standard" seq="28" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Use technology, including the Internet, to produce and publish writing and to interact and collaborate with others.</TOPIC>
</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FC7E7446-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC30E83E-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" seq="29" level="2" placeholder="N" linkable="N">Research to Build and Present Knowledge<TOPIC id="FDAF8490-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC7E7446-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="W.7" raw_state_num="7" label="Anchor Standard" seq="30" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Conduct short as well as more sustained research projects based on focused questions, demonstrating understanding of the subject under investigation.</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FDB96E2E-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC7E7446-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="W.8" raw_state_num="8" label="Anchor Standard" seq="31" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Gather relevant information from multiple print and digital sources, assess the credibility and accuracy of each source, and integrate the information while avoiding plagiarism.</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FDC3B528-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC7E7446-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="W.9" raw_state_num="9" label="Anchor Standard" seq="32" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Draw evidence from literary or informational texts to support analysis, reflection, and research.</TOPIC>
</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FC897B52-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC30E83E-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" seq="33" level="2" placeholder="N" linkable="N">Range of Writing<TOPIC id="FDD8F64A-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC897B52-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="W.10" raw_state_num="10" label="Anchor Standard" seq="34" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Write routinely over extended time frames (time for research, reflection, and revision) and shorter time frames (a single sitting or a day or two) for a range of tasks, purposes, and audiences.</TOPIC>
</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FC9B1EAC-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC30E83E-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="Note" raw_state_num="Note" seq="35" level="2" placeholder="N" linkable="N">Note on range and content of student writing<TOPIC id="FDE25244-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC9B1EAC-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="Note" raw_state_num="Note" seq="36" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">K-5 To build a foundation for college and career readiness, students need to learn to use writing as a way of offering and supporting opinions, demonstrating understanding of the subjects they are studying, and conveying real and imagined experiences and events. They learn to appreciate that a key purpose of writing is to communicate clearly to an external, sometimes unfamiliar audience, and they begin to adapt the form and content of their writing to accomplish a particular task and purpose. They develop the capacity to build knowledge on a subject through research projects and to respond analytically to literary and informational sources. To meet these goals, students must devote significant time and effort to writing, producing numerous pieces over short and extended time frames throughout the year.</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FDEBE764-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC9B1EAC-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="Note" raw_state_num="Note" seq="37" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">6-12 For students, writing is a key means of asserting and defending claims, showing what they know about a subject, and conveying what they have experienced, imagined, thought, and felt. To be college- and career- ready writers, students must take task, purpose, and audience into careful consideration, choosing words, information, structures, and formats deliberately. They need to know how to combine elements of different kinds of writing&#8212;for example, to use narrative strategies within argument and explanation within narrative&#8212;to produce complex and nuanced writing. They need to be able to use technology strategically when creating, refining, and collaborating on writing. They have to become adept at gathering information, evaluating sources, and citing material accurately, reporting findings from their research and analysis of sources in a clear and cogent manner. They must have the flexibility, concentration, and fluency to produce high-quality first-draft text under a tight deadline as well as the capacity to revisit and make improvements to a piece of writing over multiple drafts when circumstances encourage or require it.</TOPIC>
</TOPIC>
</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FC36A684-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="SL" label="Strand" seq="38" level="1" placeholder="N" linkable="N">Speaking and Listening<TOPIC id="FCA8C4DA-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC36A684-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" seq="39" level="2" placeholder="N" linkable="N">Comprehension and Collaboration<TOPIC id="FDF86282-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FCA8C4DA-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="SL.1" raw_state_num="1" label="Anchor Standard" seq="40" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Prepare for and participate effectively in a range of conversations and collaborations with diverse partners, building on others&#8217; ideas and expressing their own clearly and persuasively.</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FE02C2C2-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FCA8C4DA-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="SL.2" raw_state_num="2" label="Anchor Standard" seq="41" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Integrate and evaluate information presented in diverse media and formats, including visually, quantitatively, and orally.</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FE17EE7C-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FCA8C4DA-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="SL.3" raw_state_num="3" label="Anchor Standard" seq="42" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Evaluate a speaker&#8217;s point of view, reasoning, and use of evidence and rhetoric.</TOPIC>
</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FCB42032-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC36A684-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" seq="43" level="2" placeholder="N" linkable="N">Presentation of Knowledge and Ideas<TOPIC id="FE2134A0-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FCB42032-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="SL.4" raw_state_num="4" label="Anchor Standard" seq="44" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Present information, findings, and supporting evidence such that listeners can follow the line of reasoning and the organization, development, and style are appropriate to task, purpose, and audience.</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FE2988C6-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FCB42032-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="SL.5" raw_state_num="5" label="Anchor Standard" seq="45" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Make strategic use of digital media and visual displays of data to express information and enhance understanding of presentations.</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FE31E67E-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FCB42032-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="SL.6" raw_state_num="6" label="Anchor Standard" seq="46" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Adapt speech to a variety of contexts and communicative tasks, demonstrating command of formal English when indicated or appropriate.</TOPIC>
</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FCBDAB84-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC36A684-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="Note" raw_state_num="Note" seq="47" level="2" placeholder="N" linkable="N">Note on range and content of student speaking and listening<TOPIC id="FE37870A-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FCBDAB84-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="Note" raw_state_num="Note" seq="48" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">K-5.a To build a foundation for college and career readiness, students must have ample opportunities to take part in a variety of rich, structured conversations&#8212;as part of a whole class, in small groups, and with a partner. Being productive members of these conversations requires that students contribute accurate, relevant information; respond to and develop what others have said; make comparisons and contrasts; and analyze and synthesize a multitude of ideas in various domains.</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FE3CCCC4-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FCBDAB84-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="Note" raw_state_num="Note" seq="49" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">K-5.b New technologies have broadened and expanded the role that speaking and listening play in acquiring and sharing knowledge and have tightened their link to other forms of communication. Digital texts confront students with the potential for continually updated content and dynamically changing combinations of words, graphics, images, hyperlinks, and embedded video and audio.</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FE41F49C-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FCBDAB84-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="Note" raw_state_num="Note" seq="50" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">6-12.a To become college and career ready, students must have ample opportunities to take part in a variety of rich, structured conversations&#8212;as part of a whole class, in small groups, and with a partner&#8212;built around important content in various domains. They must be able to contribute appropriately to these conversations, to make comparisons and contrasts, and to analyze and synthesize a multitude of ideas in accordance with the standards of evidence appropriate to a particular discipline. Whatever their intended major or profession, high school graduates will depend heavily on their ability to listen attentively to others so that they are able to build on others&#8217; meritorious ideas while expressing their own clearly and persuasively.</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FE477A2A-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FCBDAB84-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="Note" raw_state_num="Note" seq="51" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">6-12.b New technologies have broadened and expanded the role that speaking and listening play in acquiring and sharing knowledge and have tightened their link to other forms of communication. The Internet has accelerated the speed at which connections between speaking, listening, reading, and writing can be made, requiring that students be ready to use these modalities nearly simultaneously. Technology itself is changing quickly, creating a new urgency for students to be adaptable in response to change.</TOPIC>
</TOPIC>
</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FC3AEE06-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="L" label="Strand" seq="52" level="1" placeholder="N" linkable="N">Language<TOPIC id="FCCF1D1A-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC3AEE06-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" seq="53" level="2" placeholder="N" linkable="N">Conventions of Standard English<TOPIC id="FE5A2968-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FCCF1D1A-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="L.1" raw_state_num="1" label="Anchor Standard" seq="54" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Demonstrate command of the conventions of standard English grammar and usage when writing or speaking.</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FE5FEA92-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FCCF1D1A-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="L.2" raw_state_num="2" label="Anchor Standard" seq="55" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Demonstrate command of the conventions of standard English capitalization, punctuation, and spelling when writing.</TOPIC>
</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FCD9032A-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC3AEE06-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" seq="56" level="2" placeholder="N" linkable="N">Knowledge of Language<TOPIC id="FE64FC12-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FCD9032A-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="L.3" raw_state_num="3" label="Anchor Standard" seq="57" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Apply knowledge of language to understand how language functions in different contexts, to make effective choices for meaning or style, and to comprehend more fully when reading or listening.</TOPIC>
</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FCE15138-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC3AEE06-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" seq="58" level="2" placeholder="N" linkable="N">Vocabulary Acquisition and Use<TOPIC id="FE6BACC4-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FCE15138-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="L.4" raw_state_num="4" label="Anchor Standard" seq="59" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Determine or clarify the meaning of unknown and multiple-meaning words and phrases by using context clues, analyzing meaningful word parts, and consulting general and specialized reference materials, as appropriate.</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FE72496C-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FCE15138-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="L.5" raw_state_num="5" label="Anchor Standard" seq="60" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Demonstrate understanding of figurative language, word relationships, and nuances in word meanings.</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FE77B3F2-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FCE15138-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="L.6" raw_state_num="6" label="Anchor Standard" seq="61" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">Acquire and use accurately a range of general academic and domain-specific words and phrases sufficient for reading, writing, speaking, and listening at the college and career readiness level; demonstrate independence in gathering vocabulary knowledge when encountering an unknown term important to comprehension or expression.</TOPIC>
</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FCE7A11E-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FC3AEE06-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="Note" raw_state_num="Note" seq="62" level="2" placeholder="N" linkable="N">Note on range and content of student language use<TOPIC id="FE7CFF56-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FCE7A11E-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="Note" raw_state_num="Note" seq="63" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">K-5 To build a foundation for college and career readiness in language, students must gain control over many conventions of standard English grammar, usage, and mechanics as well as learn other ways to use language to convey meaning effectively. They must also be able to determine or clarify the meaning of grade-appropriate words encountered through listening, reading, and media use; come to appreciate that words have nonliteral meanings, shadings of meaning, and relationships to other words; and expand their vocabulary in the course of studying content. The inclusion of Language standards in their own strand should not be taken as an indication that skills related to conventions, effective language use, and vocabulary are unimportant to reading, writing, speaking, and listening; indeed, they are inseparable from such contexts.</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FE825F46-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" parent_id="FCE7A11E-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="Note" raw_state_num="Note" seq="64" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">6-12 To be college and career ready in language, students must have firm control over the conventions of standard English. At the same time, they must come to appreciate that language is as at least as much a matter of craft as of rules and be able to choose words, syntax, and punctuation to express themselves and achieve particular functions and rhetorical effects. They must also have extensive vocabularies, built through reading and study, enabling them to comprehend complex texts and engage in purposeful writing about and conversations around content. They need to become skilled in determining or clarifying the meaning of words and phrases they encounter, choosing flexibly from an array of strategies to aid them. They must learn to see an individual word as part of a network of other words&#8212;words, for example, that have similar denotations but different connotations. The inclusion of Language standards in their own strand should not be taken as an indication that skills related to conventions, effective language use, and vocabulary are unimportant to reading, writing, speaking, and listening; indeed, they are inseparable from such contexts.</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="FE825F11-D90C-11zx-8CB5-43E6D51F4fgt" parent_id="FCE7A11E-D90C-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F4EFC" state_num="Note" raw_state_num="Note" seq="64" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="Y">New Child Topic added</TOPIC>
</TOPIC>
</TOPIC>
<TOPIC id="0E2673C4-D90D-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F1q1q" state_num="R.3" seq="3" level="3" placeholder="N" linkable="N">New Topic added</TOPIC>
</STANDARD>
<STANDARD id="B45918EA-D959-11E2-9C66-33FC9CRRREEE"><GRADE lo="PK" hi="5" seq="510" code="1">New PK to 5 grade created</GRADE>
<TOPIC id="0DBFB9C2-D90D-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F9y9y" state_num="R.1" label="Strand" seq="1" level="1" placeholder="N" linkable="N">Parent Topic added<TOPIC id="0DD5C2F8-D90D-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F8u8u" parent_id="0DBFB9C2-D90D-11E2-8CB5-43E6D51F9y9y" state_num="R.2" raw_state_num="RL" seq="2" level="2" placeholder="N" linkable="N">Child Topic-1 added
</TOPIC>
</TOPIC>
</STANDARD>

</MSS>
